[Music]
for
is
EX
that
o
is
is okay good took a while to write uh so
essentially what we do is we start off with
K arms right and then in the first round okay
so median elimination is going to proceed in
rounds okay in the first round we pull each
arm some number of times right determined by
this magic quantity so can people read this
magic quantity it's 1 by Epsilon L by 2 whole
squ log 3 by Delta L
okay so I pull each arm that many number of times
okay and then I estimate there empirical value
right qla a I'll estimate right where L indicates
that this is the Q function I'm forming at the L
stage okay then what I do is I take these QA
arrange them in ascending descending whatever
order I find the median of all these arms and then
eliminate all those arms whose values is below the
median right I'm eliminating so this is the
set difference so I take my current set SL
right these are all the arms that are under
consideration so S1 will be all the ACT arms
and then I'm eliminating all those arms such
that so my qla a is less than ml where ml is
the median at the L level right and then I
change my constants by Magic compounds again
so my Epsilon L + 1 becomes 3/4 of Epsilon
L Epsilon l itself started as Epsilon by 4
okay now it becomes 3x 4 of Epsilon by 4 and
my Delta L + 1 becomes Delta L by 2 which
already started as Delta by 2 so it becomes
Delta by 4 and Lal L + 1 and I keep going
until my SL becomes one the number of arms left
becomes one right so how many rounds will I go
block K rounds because every time I'm
eliminating half THS right because I'm
looking at the median I'm eliminating everything
below the median so I'm guaranteed to eliminate
half the arms in every round so I'll end in
log K rounds okay but the trick to provide
proving any kind of sample complexity here is
to show that okay this quantity right when I
Sumit over this lock rounds is some bounded
quantity right and that gives me the sample
complexity I want I already told you what
the sample complexity is going to be what was
it K by Epsilon s log 1 by Delta some constant
by Delta so as far as order notations we can
ignore the constant so log 1 by Delta so that
is what is going to be the sample complexity so
I'll have to show you that first second in fact
first I have to show you that this is actually a
pack algorithm right that it actually gives you
a Epsilon optimal arm with a high probability
right becomes a little tricky here because I'm
eliminating half the arms every time so now I
have to think about what is the probability
that I eliminated all the Epsilon optimal
arms right so I have to in some round along
the way before I reach the final round okay
I shouldn't eliminate all the Epsilon optimal
arms right so what we will do here you see the
right because at the end of the thing if that
one arm left is some Epsilon optimal arm I'm
safe right but along the way if I eliminate all
the Epsilon optimal arms then I'm in trouble so
what I will do now is to show that at every
round the probability of me doing that is
very small so small that when I add up the
probability of me eliminating across all the
rounds it is still below Delta right still
below Delta so that's essentially what I'm
going to try and show did that make sense so
every round the probability of me eliminating
all the Epsilon optimal arms is small so
small that when I add it up across all the
rounds it is still less than Delta okay so that's
essentially what I'm going to what I'm going to
show okay so first theorem that I'll state
it but I'll come back and prove this later is
the the median elimination algorithm takes Epsilon
Delta an Epsilon Delta
pack with
okay
so we'll prove this in two parts the first LMA
will help us establish that okay and then then
we'll have another result later that will help
us establish the sample complex sample complex
is actually trivial right if you think about
it it's essentially summing this quantity up
right starting from Epsilon by 4 and Delta
by 2 and successively changing the value of
Epsilon and Delta okay it's just just a bunch of
algebra right you just move move numbers around
and simplify things you'll get it conceptually
there is nothing deep about looking at the sample
complexity so is that clear so I essentially
have to sum up this quantity right for every
arm so this will be multiplied by the size of
the arms which will be which will start with K
and then it will become k by2 k by 4 successively
it become smaller and smaller and likewise the
Epsilon and my Delta also become smaller and
smaller so the idea is to just to Sumit over L
this quantity and then replace this by a function
of Epsilon and L you can replace Epsilon L right
by a function of Epsilon so what is Epsilon 1
it's Epsilon by 4 what is Epsilon 2 3x 4 into
Epsilon by 2 Epsilon by 4 Epsilon 3 is 3x 4 the
whole squared so so Epsilon L is essentially 3x
4^ lus 1 into Epsilon by 4 right so like that
so you can write the similar expression for
Delta and you can essentially simplify it right
so that part is fairly straightforward so if you
have time I'll just give you an intuition into
that but otherwise you can work it out easily uh
the first part is one that requires some work
right so this is what we'll do for every face
l in the median elimination algorithm we
have the
probability
is
okay so this requires a little bit of
thought so what I'm saying so what is
this this is the true best arm at Lev L right
so at level one I would expect this to be a star
right so the true best arm I'm not talking about
the capital Q right I'm talking about Q Stars here
so I'm talking about the true best arm right so in
this case I would expect the true this this should
be Q star a star right in level one but in level
two itself it could be something different because
I might have lost a star in the first round itself
right what I'm saying is okay this is the best I
could have done in the lth round right potentially
right and what is this this is the best I could
have done in the l+ one round right so the bad
case is when this is less than that right that
means I eliminated some high ranking arms all I
have left or low ranking arms right so the bad Cas
is when this quantity is less than that quantity
right by how much it should be less right that's
a question that's a trick we are asking here so if
I add an Epsilon to this so essentially I have my
uh I know let's call this J Star right that's a
maximum in the L level so I have my qar J star
here right and I have my Q star I star
here which is the guy that gives me the max
here right if I add an Epsilon to
this if I add an Epsilon to this
and this is within that that means
this is Epsilon optimal when you consider against
that right do you see that if I add
an Epsilon to this lower value and
the higher value is actually less
than that then it is a acceptable
situation because the lower value
is within Epsilon of the higher
value correct so this is a good outcome
so I'm saying the probability of the good
outcome is at least 1 minus Delta that
means the probability is high okay is
that Mak sense the probability of the good
outcome is at least 1 minus Delta okay now
the thing to notice here this is not truly
Epsilon this Epsilon L right and this is not
Delta this is Delta l so why is that the
case because every round I lose Epsilon L
right at most Epsilon L right so at the end
of the day I shouldn't have lost more than
Epsilon so what I'm going to show you is that
every round I lose Epsilon L and Epsilon L is
chosen such that even if I lose the Epsilon L
for every L My overall loss will be epon right
so that because we know that when s in S1 the
best arm is a star right and if overall loss is
less than Epsilon then at the end of this I'll
have at least one Epsilon optimal arm left okay
so that is basically what we are trying to show
here so this this this relation makes sense why
we are trying to show this okay and likewise
this 1us Delta L is there because at the end
of the day if all the events hold true also
my probability must be at least 1 minus Delta
right therefore we use Delta L and that is
the reason your Epsilon 1's and Delta 1es are
already smaller than Epsilon and Delta because if
I start off with Epsilon here and Delta here I'm
gone
[Applause]
okay so people know what w log means right
without loss of generality I'm going to
consider L equal to 1 right so whatever results
I show here will will hold for the subsequent L
right
so we start off by looking at the first the event
E1 which
is first thing I'm looking at is I'm grossly
underestimating the the True Value right I mean
this this should now start looking familiar to you
because in everything we have been doing the same
thing we start off by saying okay first thing
that has to go wrong is I grossly underestimate
the the true optimal actions value and then we'll
think about okay what happens if I overestimate
the suboptimal actions value but I start off
by saying okay grossly underestimate this
right okay so now what is the probability of
this no and we already have our magic number
here so substitute everything and tell
me so you have the expression here
right and you have the magic number
there
that this guy will get cancelled
out again do you have a four problem there
yeah yeah so well the square should be outside
I mean I I'm just writing it down from the
algorithm here so their results are wrong
right so it should be Epsilon l s by
2 not Epsilon L by 2 the whole squ
okay and this is a one-sided bound
so the outside two will not be there
right so everything will simplify and you'll
get Delta 1 by
3 okay this is the first event suppose it
doesn't hold okay suppose even as doesn't
know that essentially I've not made a bad mistake
underestimating the best arm right and since it's
maybe I should have done it slightly differently
um I have said without loss of generality consider
L equal to one but then I put in a star here which
actually violates the without loss of generality
part okay so the a star here is actually the best
arm left at level l that's how you should think
of it it's not the overall best arm whatever
be the level L it's a best arm left at level
L and for L equal to one it happens to be a
star the true a star right for for L equal
2 3 and four this will essentially become
the best arm at that level so I'll just put
a l there so that you know what I'm meaning
okay it's the best arm in the Heth level
that is left among all the arms that is left
the true best arm in the health level okay
good
okay so next I'm going to look at the
probability that this translation is killing me
sh up EX
hm this one put the two in
the numerator I should put
the two in the numerator what do
you need for it to cancel out uh
Epsilon have Epsilon 1 by 2 so Epsilon 1 by
no yeah so this is Epsilon by 2 so substitute
that I get Epsilon squ by 4 right that will
become half that's one by Epsilon squ by
2 so it will get things are all fine okay
good so I'm going to look at
this problem right so sorry not
this so E1 does not hold that means that this
is true right so E1 is the event where I have
underestimated it so I'm saying E1 does not hold
that means that it is no longer an underestimate
so this is my estimate is within Epsilon by 2
right but then I'm looking at the possib ility
that different yeah so but my some J which is
not Epsilon 1 optimal right so that's that's a
condition
no on L uh right so I know that current my
current estimate in the lth round I'm going
to decide about eliminating in the lth
round right in the current round I not
underestimated my a star L okay so it's I'm
within Epsilon of that within Epsilon 1 by
two of the true a star value right but then I
take some other arm J which is a bad arm bad
in the sense J is not Epsilon L close to a star
it's a bad arm right and I figured out what is
the probability that the Q estimate for that
arm will be greater than the Q estimate for
the a star right so if this happens right
then there's a chance that a star will get
eliminated right only a chance why
it has to be in the lower half not
just get beaten by one guy but it has
to be in the lower half of the arms
right so I need at least K by 2 or whatever
uh the size of SK SL by two bad arms to beat
me correct for me to eliminate this arm right
I need at least half of the arms to beat me
not just one arm right but before we go to that
part so what is the probability of this happening
well so this conditioning tells us that ql a
star is not too bad right so what does that
mean qlj has to be more than Epsilon by2
so we remember that figure we drew right
so either this has to be underestimate well I
erase the figure but either the a star has to
be underestimated by more than Epsilon by
2 or the a prime has to be overestimated
by more than Epsilon by 2 right here we are
conditioning it on the event that a star is
not underestimated by more than Epsilon by2
therefore J has to be overestimated by more
than Epsilon by 2 right since this event we have
conditioned it as false so that event has to be
true okay
so what do we get in that
case same thing here
right so I'm kind of skipping a step here but
people are all fine with that right I'm skipping
rewriting this this bound right so essentially you
have to now replace this with overestimating by
Epsilon by 2 right in fact I should probably just
make you write that missing step as a homework so
that I I'm sure that people are all comfortable
with the notation nothing more the notation can
get really complex otherwise the concepts are
very simple that is why I'm taking so much time
talking over it right if I could just write
the proof and leave it at that because it's
fairly easy these things are fairly easy so
this is for one arm right and like this they
have K arms right so the
probability uh
good so let uh I don't know we use the same
symbols here which I don't agree with let hash
bad be the number of bad arms okay hash bad be the
number of bad arms such that this this condition
holds right hash bad be the number
of bad arms such that that condition
holds so these are the number of
bad arms that are beating the best
arm
for
so what will that expectation
be
huh mod by 2 yeah not really but
uh I agree with the mod SL part but not SL by two
I have a probability for that happening right and
how many such experiments actually is mod SL
minus one right potentially everything other
than the best arm could be a bad arm right at at
maximum thing is SL minus one right and so it's
SL -1 into Delta 1 by 3 so that's the probability
of one arm being bad I mean one arm actually for
which this first relation holds for one bad arm
and there are SL minus one I'm just making it SL
to make our life easier so SL s bad arms so the
expected number of bad arms will be SL into Delta
1x3 right now I want to look at the probability
that hash
bad
this is where we are going to use
the marco
inequality right so I already written
the expectation here so I'm asking you
the probability of X greater than
equal to a it's the expected value
of x divided by a right so this is less
than or equal to the expected value which
is divided by
a
okay so what have we shown there is that if E1
does not hold if I'm good in my estimate for
the best arm okay the probability that half
the I mean so many bad arms will beat me is
bounded by two Dela 1 by 3 right but I'm also
considering E1 as a bad event right E1 is also
bad because I my estimate for the best arm
is really bad you know so all bets are off
in some sense right because I don't really
I can't really identify my best St because
it's so bad right so all bets are also even
is also a bad event right all of this is bad
and even is also bad so what is the total
probability of something bad happening the
two together but they huh use the union
bound you want use a fancy term we use
the union bound and then we say the probability
of something bad happening is bounded by Delta
1 right so this bad is Delta 1 by 3 that
bad is 2 Delta 1 by3 and this is actually
the compliment event of E1 in fact I can just add
the probabilities I don't really need the union
Bond so the total probability of something bad
happening is Delta 1 right so that's essentially
what we are started off by saying here so
the probability of good is 1 minus Delta
now we have shown that the probability of bad is
Delta l so the probability of good is 1us Delta
L okay
great so one of the the nice things about the
median elmination algorithm is that uh it was one
of the earliest papers to introduce this kind of
a round based algorithms to the Bandit literature
right now a lot of uh later uh improvements on
both regret based case and people trying to play
around with the uh uh the pack guarantees all
have switched to some kind of round based idea
you know so you do a certain number of pulls and
then you eliminate a certain number of arms right
and then go back and pull the remaining arms some
more and then eliminate some more arms so these
kinds of round based elimination methods have
become very popular in the Pandit literature and
the Medan elimination is one of the earliest such
round based uh elimination approaches and after
this became very popular and a lot of papers uh
started being written using this kind of a round
based idea right so we have so far what we have
shown is that it is have we shown that it is uh
back huh what is it oh that is fine I mean that
that I'm already spoken about this LMA is taken
As proved right this LMA has taken As proved yeah
so you have to still use the union bond for every
round that I'm eliminating right so what you
have to show show is well I have all these
Deltas right so you have to keep adding them up to
make sure that eventually you are less
than overall you are less than Delta
right so every round the probability of failure
is bounded by Delta 1 right so for the K rounds
the probability of failure is I mean whatever
the uh log K rounds the probability of failure
is bounded by summing it up so Delta 2 Delta by 2
Delta by 4 Delta by 8 and so on so forth until you
reach one right so that's the that's the summation
and or not until you reach one until you reach log
K rounds so it's you'll get Delta by 2 power
log k okay and the summation of that will go
to Delta is essentially Delta into half + 1/4
+ 1/8 right if the sum runs to Infinity you'll
get 1 but the sum is not running to Infinity
it stops at some finite time so it will be
less than one so the summation will be less
than Delta Pro right so some probability of
something bad happening will be less than Delta
so likewise you can show the same things for uh
the Epsilon right so at every level you you
drop atmost by Epsilon L right so the total
you would have dropped is Epsilon by 4 + so
it's essentially 1/4 plus uh what is it uh 34
into one or or yeah right so Epsilon by 4 into 1
+ 1/4 and so on so forth right 3x 4 L minus one
yeah yeah that that is also upper bounded
by one if you run it to Infinity no it's
yeah it's upper bound it be one if you
run the summation to Infinity but you're
stopping at some finite amount so it'll be
less than Epsilon okay so both of that are
satisfied that is easy enough uh the harder
the trickier part is to show the the sample
complexity
right it's not hard it's just algebra can
you let you guys do it or you want me to
do the sample complexity part of the proof as
well no is it huh depends somebody say depends
depends on what that's a paper is it there in
the paper it is there in the paper yeah yeah
it's it's there in the paper you can look at it
and so I'll stop it here for the pack the pack
complexity we'll come back to all of this regret
and pack and everything when we look at the full
RL problem at some point uh but right now for
the bandits I'll stop [Music] [Applause] here